Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ records, 1928-2020.
Congregational Library & Archives
Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ records, 1928-2020.
RG5477
Congregational Library & Archives
11.22 Cubic Feet
(10 boxes)
The Council of Congregational Women of Connecticut was organized on October 2, 1928. The organization changed names numerous times over the course of its history but on May 13, 1997, became the Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ. From the time of the organization's founding in 1928, it divided itself into districts representing four geographical regions in Connecticut: the Eastern district, the Hartford district, the Litchfield district, and a fourth district called the New Haven district until 1973 when its name was changed to the Southwestern district. To communicate with and guide its members, the group has maintained an active program of writing and publishing a range of publications, and it has also planned a range of programs providing opportunities for its members to worship, study, and participate in service together. The organization's records document the changing roles of women in the church and society during the group's history. Records include meeting records, annual reports, governance and officers' records, records of sub-committees and districts, newsletters, guidebooks, correspondence, mailing lists, financial records, program and event records, histories and scrapbooks, and photographs.
Connecticut Fellowship of Congregational-Christian Women
Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ
Council of Congregational-Christian Women of Connecticut
Fellowship of Congregational-Christian Women of Connecticut
Southern New England United Church of Christ Women's Connection
Women's Fellowship of the Connecticut Conference of the United Church of Christ
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Nine cartons of materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Southern New England United Church of Christ Women's Connection in October, 2023; Accession 2023-50. An additional two cartons were donated by the Southern New England United Church of Christ in February, 2024, as part of an accrual to the General Association of Connecticut records; Accession 2024-11.
Historical
The Council of Congregational Women of Connecticut was organized on October 2, 1928, in a meeting at Center Church in Hartford, Connecticut. On December 31, 1926, the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions and the Women's Board of Missions had merged. Congregational women across the country were reorganizing themselves as a result of this merger, and in Connecticut this reorganization took the form of the Council of Congregational Women of Connecticut. The Council itself represented a merger of four former organizations: the Women's Congregational Home Missionary Union of Connecticut, and three branches of the Women's Board of Missions in New Haven, Hartford, and Eastern Connecticut.
The women's organization has changed names numerous times over the course of its history. On April 22, 1936, the organization became the Council of Congregational-Christian Women of Connecticut. On April 23, 1947, it became the Fellowship of Congregational-Christian Women of Connecticut. The organization changed names again on April 19, 1950, becoming the Connecticut Fellowship of Congregational-Christian Women. When in 1964 the Connecticut State Conference changed its name to the Connecticut Conference of the United Church of Christ, the women's organization followed suit and revised its name once again, becoming on October 6, 1964, the Women's Fellowship of the Connecticut Conference of the United Church of Christ. On May 13, 1997, the organization adopted a name that would better reflect the combination of lay and clergy women in the organization: the Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ. Finally, on January 1, 2020, when the Connecticut Conference joined the Southern New England Conference United Church of Christ, the women's organization adopted the name that it uses today, Southern New England United Church of Christ Women's Connection.
From the time of the organization's founding in 1928, it divided itself into districts representing four geographical regions in Connecticut: the Eastern district, the Hartford district, the Litchfield district, and a fourth district called the New Haven district until 1973 when its name was changed to the Southwestern district. A set of elected officers have led the organization, and it has also executed its administrative and programming functions by means of a variety of sub-committees. To communicate with and guide its members, the group has maintained an active program of writing, editing, and publishing a range of publications: reading lists; various guidebooks for program planning, worship, study, service, and leadership; several newsletters; and booklets to facilitate and document annual meetings.
The group has held regular state-wide and district meetings for administrative and organizational purposes. It has also planned a range of programs providing opportunities for its members to worship, study, and participate in service together. These include leadership training conferences, quiet days, retreats, workshops, trips, and service programs. In the organization's early decades, it maintained a lending library for its members. In 1955, the organization supported efforts to assist churches in the Housatonic Valley flooded by Hurricane Diane. In 1987, it joined the United Church of Christ boycott of California table grapes.
The organization's records document the changing roles of women in the church and society and their efforts to recognize women as equal church members and leaders. The records of the Task Force on the Status of Women in Church and Society, the Advisory Commission on Women, the Committee on Women's Concerns, and the Coordinating Center for Women in Church and Society document the organization's efforts to redefine women's roles in the church in the wake of women's changing roles in society in the 1960s, 1970s, and early 1980s. The organization's Honored Laywomen Award, starting in the 1990s, recognized lay women leaders, and the Pioneer Women Clergy event of 2016 recognized early women clergy members. In 2012, the group drafted the Resolution on Women as Equal Partners in Church and Society, a document affirming their support of women as equals.
The organization continues today to provide opportunities for regional women to join together in worship, study, and service.
Content Description
This collection contains the records of the Connecticut Women of United Church of Christ, now called the Southern New England United Church of Christ Women's Connection. It includes administrative records, including meeting records, annual reports, governance and officers' records, and the records of sub-committees and districts; communications materials, including newsletters, guidebooks, correspondence, and mailing lists; financial records, including budgets, treasurers' reports, receipts, and invoices; records of programs, events, and initiatives; scrapbooks; and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series. The first series is further arranged into four sub-series, and the third series is further arranged into five sub-series. Records in each series and subseries have been primarily arranged chronologically by start date, and secondarily by topic.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1928-2020
Subseries 1: Annual meetings and reports, 1928-2019
Subseries 2: Executive and State Board meetings, 1928-2019
Subseries 3: Governance and officers' records, 1928-2020
Subseries 4: Sub-committee records, 1931-2006
Series 2: Communications, 1928-2019
Series 3: District records, 1928-2011
Subseries 1: Litchfield district records, 1928-1990
Subseries 2: Hartford district records, 1928-2007
Subseries 3: Eastern district records, 1928-2011
Subseries 4: New Haven district records, 1928-1980
Subseries 5: Southwestern district records, 1967-2010
Series 4: Financial records, 1941-2020
Series 5: Programming and initiatives, 1944-2019
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
A cassette player is required to access material on cassette tape, and a CD player is required to access material on CD.
Associations, institutions, etc.; Church work with women.; Women -- Books and reading.; Women -- Religious life.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Women Clergy.; Women in charitable work.; Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ
- Administrative records, 1928 2020; 1928-2020; 96 Folders; 4 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the administrative records of the Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ. Included are records of annual meetings and State Board and Executive Board meetings, records kept by the organization's presidents and other officers, organizational histories and scrapbooks, and records of the group's sub-committees.
  - Annual meetings and reports, 1928 2019; 1928-2019; 18 Folders; 1 Volume
    This subseries contains records pertaining to the annual meetings of the organization, including minutes, annual reports, meeting programs and booklets, photographs, and an audio recording on cassette tape.
    - Annual meeting programs, 1928 1944; 1928-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual meeting programs, 1945 1995; 1945-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annual reports, 1955 1964; 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Annual reports, 1965 1979; 1965-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annual reports, 1980 1984; 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Annual reports, 1985 1989; 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual reports, 1990 1995; 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual meeting announcements, 1964 1978; 1964-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Annual meeting minutes, 1964 2006; 1964-2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual meeting photographs, 1975 1990; 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Annual meeting photographs, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Annual meeting photograph album, 1976 1982; 1976-1982 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    - 50th annual meeting cassette, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Annual meeting booklets, 1991 1999; 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Annual meeting booklets, 2000 2006; 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Annual meeting booklets, 2007 2013; 2007-2013 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Annual meeting booklets, 2014 2019; 2014-2019 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Remarks from past presidents for the 75th annual meeting, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Annual meeting CD, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Executive and State Board meetings, 1928 2019; 1928-2019; 14 Folders; 1 Volume
    This subseries contains records pertaining to the organization's Executive Board meetings and State Board meetings. Included are agendas, minutes, notebooks, and photographs.
    - Executive Board meeting minutes, 1928 1931; 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Executive Board meeting minutes, 1941 2010; 1941-2010 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 1936 1956; 1936-1956 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 1949 1979; 1949-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 1980 1989; 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 1990 1999; 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 2000 2009; 2000-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 2010 2014; 2010-2014 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - State Board meeting minutes, 2015 2019; 2015-2019, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - State Board and Executive Committee attendee's notebook, 1956 1962; 1956-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - State Board meeting agendas, 1964 2018; 1964-2018 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Executive Board meeting agendas, 1968 2016; 1968-2016 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - State Board Share-in meetings, 1972 2017; 1972-2017 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - State Board meeting photographs, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - State Board and annual meeting notebook, 1998 2005; 1998-2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Governance and officers' records, 1928 2020; 1928-2020; 31 Folders; 2 Volumes
    This subseries contains records pertaining to the history, governance, and officers of the organization. Included are organizational histories and scrapbooks; officer lists and ballots; descriptions of officers' duties; records kept by presidents and secretaries; versions of the organization's constitution, by-laws, and manual; and records documenting policy votes and organizational planning and goals.
    - Histories, 1928 2019; 1928-2019, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Officer lists, 1928 2019; 1928-2019, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1938 1947; 1938-1947 (Box 9, Volume 7)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1949 2012; 1949-2012, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Secretary's notebook, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Secretary's notebook, 1955 1958; 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Scrapbook, 1953 1958; 1953-1958 (Box 9, Volume 1)
      Separated Materials
      Materials removed from the front cover of this scrapbook can be found in Correspondence and clippings about August 1955 flood, 1955-1956, located in the Administrative series, Governance and officers' records sub-series.
    - Correspondence and clippings about August 1955 flood, 1955 1956; 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Items in this folder were removed from the front cover of Scrapbook, 1953-1958, located in the Administrative series, Governance and officers' records subseries.
    - District organization and governance, 1958 2006; 1958-2006, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - President profiles, 1960 2016; 1960-2016, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - President Alice Smith records, 1962 1966; 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Policy votes, 1964 1974; 1964-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - President Sally Riis records, 1965 1966; 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Officer ballots, 1965 1976; 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Department of Lay Life and Work, 1965 1978; 1965-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - President Vola Martin records, 1967 1968; 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Duties of the Officers, 1967 1977; 1967-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - President Margery Weed records, 1968 1970; 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - President Dot Oldenfield records, 1970 1972; 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - President Sarah Houk records, 1973 1974; 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - President Jane Inderstrodt records, 1974 1976; 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - President Betty Woodman records, 1976 1978; 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Goal statement, 1978 1979; 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Redistricting records, 1985 1988; 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Member notebook, 1985 1991; 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Member notebook, 1985 1991; 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Inventories of owned items, 1989 2016; 1989-2016 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Long-range planning meeting, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - President Betty Work notebook, 2004 2016; 2004-2016 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Standing rules, 2007, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Present and future conversation, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Manual, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - President lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Sub-committee records, 1931 2006; 1931-2006; 33 Folders
    This subseries contains the records of the organization's sub-committees, task forces, and commissions. Included are annual reports, planning and event records, and records kept by sub-committee leaders.
    - Annual committee reports, 1931 1932; 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Annual committee reports, 1932 1933; 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Annual committee reports, 1933 1934; 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Annual committee reports, 1934 1935; 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Annual committee reports, 1935 1936; 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Annual committee reports, 1936 1937; 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Annual committee reports, 1937 1938; 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Annual committee reports, 1938 1939; 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Annual committee reports, 1939 1940; 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Annual committee reports, 1940 1941; 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Annual committee reports, 1941 1942; 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Devotional Life and Worship Committee, 1953 1955; 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Christian Education Committee, 1955 1965; 1955-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Christian Stewardship Committee, 1956 1973; 1956-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee Mrs. Howard Orr Record Book I, 1956 1959; 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee Mrs. Howard Orr Record Book II, 1956 1959; 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee packet, 1958 1960; 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee, Mrs. Lorne A. MacLean records, 1959 1962; 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee packet, 1960 1961; 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Missionary Education Committee, 1960 1978; 1960-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Nominating Committee, 1961 1979; 1961-1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee, Mrs. Clifford O. Simpson Folder 1, 1962 1964; 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee, Mrs. Clifford O. Simpson Folder 2, 1962 1964; 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Social Action Committee, 1962 1964; 1962-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Material Aid Service Committee, 1962 1964; 1962-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Evangelism and Spiritual Life Committee, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Service Committee, 1967 1975; 1967-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Worship Committee, 1967 1977; 1967-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Task Force on the Status of Women in Church and Society, 1973 1975; 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Study Committee, 1973 2006; 1973-2006 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Advisory Commission on Women, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Committee on Women's Concerns, 1977 1979; 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Mission Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Communications, 1928 2019; 1928-2019; 36 Folders
  This series contains the communications materials of the Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ. Included are organizational publications, reading lists, guidebooks, newsletters, presidents' letters and bulletins, correspondence, and address cards.
  - Presidents' letters, 1928 1950; 1928-1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Presidents' letters, 1964 2008; 1964-2008 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Reading lists and Adventures in Reading, 1928 1977; 1928-1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Year Book, 1930 1933; 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1939 1964; 1939-1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1965 1966; 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1967 1969; 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1970 1971; 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1972 2018; 1972-2018 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Speakers and program resources, 1946 1973; 1946-1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Speakers and program resources, 1974 1998; 1974-1998, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Guide Book, 1951 1992; 1951-1992 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Devotional Life and Worship Guide, 1957 1958; 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Almanacs and Digests, 1960 1964; 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Service Guide, 1973 1998; 1973-1998 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Service Guide, 2001 2004; 2001-2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Presidents' reports, 1974 1978; 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter, 1981 1987; 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Worship Guide, 1982 1993; 1982-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Nominating Guide, 1990 1991; 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Leadership Guide, 1990 1996; 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Study Guide, 1990 1999; 1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Whole Church Resource Guide, 1990 2010; 1990-2010 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Promotional brochures, 1991 2016; 1991-2016 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Directories and Calendars, 1993 2019; 1993-2019 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Words of Women, 1994 1999; 1994-1999, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Connecticut Communicator, 1999 2005; 1999-2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Communicator, 2005 2009; 2005-2009 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Communicator, 2010 2013; 2010-2013 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Communicator, 2014 2019; 2014-2019 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Recipes from Connecticut Women of the UCC, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Calendar Girls, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Address cards, A-E, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Address cards, F-L, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Address cards, M-R, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Address cards, S-Z, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
- District records, 1928 2011; 1928-2011; 79 Folders; 6 Volumes
  This series contains the records of the districts of the Connecticut Women of the United Church of Christ. The districts represent the four geographical regions of Connecticut: the Eastern district, the Hartford district, the Litchfield district, and a fourth district called the New Haven district until 1973 when its name was changed to the Southwestern district. Included in the series are district officer lists and ballots, lists of event dates, mailing lists, program announcements, meeting programs, and scrapbooks.
  - Litchfield district records, 1928 1990; 1928-1990; 13 Folders; 3 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records of the Litchfield district, including district officer lists and ballots, mailing lists, lists of event dates, program announcements, meeting programs, annual reports, notebooks, and scrapbooks. Records pertaining jointly to the Southwestern and Litchfield districts are located in the Southwestern district subseries.
    - Bulletins, 1928 1934; 1928-1934 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - District notebook, 1928 1958; 1928-1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - District notebook, 1928 1958; 1928-1958 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Officer lists, 1938 1990; 1938-1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Litchfield district scrapbook, 1955 1965; 1955-1965 (Box 9, Volume 4)
    - Mailing lists, 1957 1979; 1957-1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Litchfield district scrapbook, 1958 1974; 1958-1974 (Box 10, Volume 2)
    - Board meetings, 1959 1973; 1959-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Meeting programs, 1959 1978; 1959-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Program announcements, 1959 1981; 1959-1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Annual reports, 1960 1965; 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Other district records, 1960 1976; 1960-1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Annual meetings, 1963 1970; 1963-1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Event date lists, 1964 1983; 1964-1983 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Officer ballots, 1970 1980; 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Litchfield district scrapbook, 1975 1990; 1975-1990 (Box 9, Volume 6)
  - Hartford district records, 1928 2007; 1928-2007; 26 Folders; 1 Volume
    This subseries contains the records of the Hartford district, including district officer lists and ballots, mailing lists, lists of event dates, program announcements, meeting programs, annual reports, financial records, officer notebooks, and a scrapbook.
    - District records, 1928 1956; 1928-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Officer lists, 1937 1992; 1937-1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Hartford district scrapbook, 1946 1959; 1946-1959 (Box 9, Volume 2)
    - Meeting programs, 1946 1978; 1946-1978 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Annual reports, 1955 1965; 1955-1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Mailing lists, 1957 1979; 1957-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - By-laws, 1958 1974; 1958-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Board meeting records, 1958 1973; 1958-1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Program attendance records, 1958 1974; 1958-1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)